we have a lot of choices to make about
our diet add to that knowing the right
thing when it comes to preventing or
treating a chronic disease fighting a
virus or losing weight and suddenly our
nutrition choices can seem almost
overwhelming well I'm here to help
welcome to the nutrition facts podcast
I'm your host Dr Michael Greger I'm back
on my treadmill today ready to answer a
multitude of your questions including
whether or not it's a good idea to get
full body MRI or CAT scans and the
benefits of protein restriction plus
I'll share with you a few dietary
Secrets okay this is from Aiden says
what are your thoughts on full body MRI
scan to detects cancer at an early stage
are the benefits outweigh the harms and
the answer is no they would not now
you'd think it's really interesting so
this brings up the concept of
over-diagnosis you'd think oh my God
that's exactly what we want right
because then you can get you nip any
budding tumor before they hurt you the
problem is most people have cancer but
most people die with their cancer rather
than from their cancer and so if the
cancer is not going to affect you in any
way in your lifetime you don't want to
know about it because the then you just
suffer you have no benefits I mean the
thing is when you find it you have no
idea if it's gonna hurt you or not so of
course you got to do something about it
and so whether it's you know surgery
chemo radiation whatever you certainly
have downsides from that and if in
actual holiday you would have never been
affected by this tumor in the first
place so all risks no benefit
um and so almost everyone dies with
thyroid cancers
um like it's over 90 percent
um on autopsies people have thyroid
cancers but 90 of people don't know they
have thyroid cancer so you don't want to
know
um similarly when you do uh you know if
you look at uh car accident victims
women in their 30s significant
percentage I forget I think it's about a
quarter of women in the 30s have uh
breast cancers
um but many the hope is that it'll grow
so slowly that they never even know it
by the time they died from something
else
um and so because of overdiagnosis you
have to be very careful about cancer
screening and there are a few cancer
screenings that are undeniably useful
you can actually have randomized control
trials showing you actually
um uh affect all cause mortality
actually save people's lives
and that cervical cancer screening
um with pelvic exams and uh Colwell
rectal cancer screening
um and there's a whole bunch of reasons
to do that and then there's certainly
pros and cons of other screening methods
but not as um are both much less
certainty in terms of uh benefit for all
cosmetality and that includes PSA
testing and mammograms and oral cancer
screenings Etc anyway
um great question and kind of
counter-intuitive answer but in the end
we actually
don't want to know in many cases and
full body and so it could start us down
some Therapeutic Pathways that would
actually do us more harm than good
here we go next question
uh Donna Dana
says uh you said carrageenan extract
isn't good but his whole Irish
or CMOS good as a source of iodine ah
okay so um
um Iris c moss is where they get
carrageenan from
packed with carrageenan um and we know
that at least the carrageenan used in
the food industry
um may cause intestinal inflammation
um I was I'm just um starting now that
the next book how not to age is done and
then just in fact checking and editing
stages I've started to script uh my next
batch of videos from nutritionfacts.org
and I'm going to do an update on the
carrageena story
um uh so we'll see where that leads us
but um for that reason alone I would
assume that Iris CMOS just because the
card gaming content if Kerrigan isn't
good for you then I receive Moss
probably isn't good for you either and I
don't know what the iodine content is
um I would stick to
um ones that I do know which is
something like Dulce or RMA or Nori
um stay away from kelp because there's
too much iodine and stay away from
hajiki because it has too much arsenic
next up Kirsten are frozen greens like
countless finish as nutritious and fresh
as fresh in fact sometimes can be more
nutritious because they were actually
Frozen the day of picking
um as opposed to you know wilting for a
week on the shelf and then in your
crisper a losing Nutri being exposed
uh and uh and losing nutrition every day
so Frozen greens pre-chopped pre-washed
um uh you know basically lasts forever
in the freezer so you don't have to keep
going getting greens every day
um or instacarting them uh and so you
look at my freezer it's half frozen
berries half Frozen greens
um and so I'm a huge fan and I say go
for it
okay next up Phyllis says how to reduce
swelling in the legs after heart surgery
um and so uh as always we need to treat
the cause it's basically three reasons
that we have swelling or so-called edema
in the legs that's problems with our
kidneys problems with the living room
problem with our heart
um if it's a heart surgery issue then
perhaps we're talking about heart
failure
um in that um your heart just can't uh
effectively
um pump blood throughout your body so it
kind of pull and stagnate in the legs
um there are some things like
compression stockings and elevation that
can decrease the swelling but really
um it's all about finding out the cause
and treating the cause whenever possible
okay HG says oh what am I eating today
oh my purple sweet potato Asian smoothie
is fantastic that's very sweet I wish I
could have a purple sweet potato in fact
I just ordered a bunch yesterday
um and the store didn't have any so I
moved oh many of you know to rural
Virginia recently and there is a long
list of things I can't find anymore that
I did when I actually lived in
Civilization
I'm in a big city
um and so for example I can't get purple
sweet potatoes
and I can't get lesson out okay oh my
favorite kind of kale on this whole long
list of stuff
I can't get my favorite unsweetened so
I'm milk yeah anyway
it's beautiful out here and uh there's
lots of Wildlife and trees and there's
certainly some parks but I do miss my
purple sweet potatoes anyway what am I
eating today
um this morning oh this morning I had my
crayon I forget what I called my palm
cran chocolate Bowl thing I actually
have a it's one of the few things I have
a cooking video about Dr Greger in the
kitchen it's the last one I did see if
you just search for Pomegranate uh
nutrition facts though it'll pop up it's
a great video
um and actually it's because mostly the
editing is just so good so really isn't
me it's just we got great editors it's
funny uh and delicious so yeah because
pomegranate season don't miss out yeah
it's only like two months when I can
enjoy pomegranates and they're gone or
at least certainly I'm glad I can find
pomegranates around here oh and then
lunch I had some leftover pasta whole
way pasta with tomato sauce made from
you know no salts do tomatoes put in the
blender and and then tons of veggies and
uh yeah kale and capers and and uh and
and garlic and onions obviously what
else I put in there the pepper
lots of spices uh balsamic vinegar
anyway delicious
um also I made that like three days ago
but uh had a little left over oh and
then
um uh supper time uh probably after this
I'll be able to eat before my next
interview
um and I got another leftovers which was
um leftover chili actually with sweet
potatoes kidney beans black beans
more canned tomatoes
um lots of chili powder oh and then
umbral on my you know purple barley
lentil Oak roads Rye Berry mixture my
Prebiotic mix
um oh and then with a whole bunch of
kale
um just regular curly kale because you
can't get the good stuff anyway if
anyone comes to visit bring me some kale
all right next is from swag astronomer
oh other than what common anything else
for herpes great question that's the
only thing I've run across although no
yeah I'm thinking of HPV for green tea
yeah I haven't run across anything else
um uh although I have not done a search
so um I will do a search in my last in
my uh batch for my next videos and see
if there's anything else about herpetic
infections great question thank you
Lisa Cal can you oh the green oh the
Prebiotic mix okay bro although now I've
I've added so many new stuff it's really
doesn't spell Burl anymore but so the b
stands for barley
um I get some wonderful purple barley
um R stands for Rye so you can get rye
berries o stands for oats so use oat
Groats the whole Oak growth
um and then L is for lentils I use this
little Beluga lentils but also add
sorghum now found a source of red
sorghum amazing
um so it's like rolls and then I have
millet
um what kind of millet it's really funky
kind of millet so Millet actually as you
know isn't a real thing there's no such
thing as milk just means small grains
there's like dozens of millets well we
think of as melt it's just Pearl Millet
one of many millets they're all
different planes with different effects
um but this is finger finger melon tell
you finger Mill it and red sorghum what
else there's something else I put in
there
I think that's it so it's like rolls um
something I need a better acronym and so
yeah you could swap out the
um Rye and uh
Barley if you wanted a gluten-free
version okay Jay says when's the last
time I was sick last month with coven
it's been years since I've been sick
um and I haven't and I hadn't gotten
covered and it's funny I kept telling
everyone no problem avoiding covert you
know just avoid you know crowded indoor
spaces for long periods of time
so I tell everyone that and then what do
I do I go to a crowded indoor space for
a long period of time get covered
ironically it was that a plant-based
nutrition government the national
plant-based nutrition conference oh I
went there and got covered in fact uh
this is sad I actually canceled I was
gonna switch to Virtual
um I I was originally I'd be there in
person I was like you know I could just
do it virtually it's not as fun I miss
everybody want to see everyone but you
know it's not worth getting covered over
it I hate being sick on the road you
know switch to Virtual but then I'm like
I want to see everybody I've been stuck
in my house for years and so as I
finally okay and so I was just so
excited to tell the organizers I'm
coming
covered be damned got coming ah anyway
and actually suffered from and I've kind
of this rare side effect which continues
to bug me so anyway
I should take my own advice
next up
Mike says we're oh but oh would I
recommend take vegans taking vitamin K2
something I just did a webinar on that
um and the answer is no why
um because there's uh no data suggesting
vitamin K2 does anything the vitamin K1
doesn't do
um and vitamin K1 where is that found
and found in dark green leafy vegetables
um and so there's purported benefits of
K2 for heart and bones and um our bones
and what was the other thing hard bones
are the third anyway it doesn't work for
any of them in fact there was a big
Scandal of fraudulent data fabrication
anyway even if we did find out there are
some unique benefits to vitamin K2 our
body makes K2 not only a microbiome from
vitamin K1 but the cells in our body
make k2 from K1 just like the animals
that we eat they're animals War animals
mammals do it we're mammals so we make
k2
um from the K1 that we eat but of course
we have to eat K1 how do we do that eat
our greens
um Kira says can diet oh yeah that can
cause pancreatitis
um I have pancreatic insufficiency but
don't drink or smoke so yeah so alcohol
um alcohol binge can give you
pancreatitis
um but pancreatic insufficiency
you know there's two functions main
functions of the pancreas there's the
endocrine functions or like making
insulin and the exocrine functions
actually spits out hormones to abduct
into our digestive tract
um helps with digestion and that's what
you typically think of with pancreatic
insufficiency though I that's I don't
think of that as being related
necessarily drinking or smoking so
ideally treat the cause
um and then there are some dietary
tweaks if there's nothing you can do to
kind of help with the symptoms
pancreatic insufficiency but ideally
find out what's causing the first place
treat the cause and reverse the
condition that's always the uh the best
way to go Jonah says how to eat when you
already had to mention how to pressure
hospitals and Care Homes to give this
food oh good question well you know Dr
Dean ornish right now after conquering
killing number one heart disease and uh
showing the first time in a randomized
control trial you can actually
um reverse the progression of cancer in
this case early stage prostate cancer
with the plant-based diet says all right
I'm just getting started let's see if we
can reverse Alzheimer's disease with the
whole world plant-based diet
um and it's currently running that trial
now we don't have the results back yet
it's not done but I'm excited to report
what it does
and if we do find out that indeed
um diets can help then it's all about
getting good food to our loved ones in
terms of individual Foods there's lots
associated with prevention trying to
think of any
um but the only thing comes to mind
immediately in terms of slowing the
progression
um would be controlling cardiovascular
risk factors so controlled cholesterol
high blood pressure can actually slow
the progression of Alzheimer's dementia
which certainly has to do with our food
um there will be certainly a lot more
the biggest chapter is uh the dementia
chapter preserving your mind in how not
to age looking forward to that coming
out in fact if I didn't have so many
questions I could look up that chapter
right now and see if there's any
particular
um foods that have been put to the test
nothing jumps to mind it's mostly in the
prevention realm um unfortunately
okay please help says Rose do I know of
anything about ehlers danlos
um yes that's like this hyper
flexibility
um syndrome ah just diagnosed of a whole
food plant-based diet
oh stomach pain I wonder if that's
related so you typically think of um
Ruble danlos uh with like problems with
one's heart uh problems with ones uh you
can run into joint problems there's skin
changes
I don't think of of uh severe stomach
pain so I'm going to assume that that's
a separate
um and so one shouldn't just kind of
ignore it it's like oh well I got this
syndrome so that's why I got stomach
pain you really you're not your
physician really your or your Healthcare
professional really should look into why
you have severe stomach pain
and it could be something serious and
something easily fixable
um some like an ulcer or something
um and so you want to get that checked
out oh serious says can uh caffeine
really affect anxiety
that's a good question
um let's uh let's look really quick show
me
um oh I'm doing a whole series on
anxiety oh although I don't think I'm I
I cover caffeine so yeah in in scripting
my next you know the uspsdf the United
States preventive Services Task Force
recently suggested uh we should be
screening kids for anxiety
um which seems like a huge gift to the
pharmaceutical industry this thing going
to want to um drug these kids but the
question is so what are their what are
the lifestyle approaches to anxiety
um and so I'm going to do a whole series
um and so you know I'll include looking
into something like caffeine let's look
at uh on anxiety for those with panic
disorder it turns out
um
yeah
um so caffeine dose is roughly
equivalent to five cups of coffee and
Deuces panic attacks in a large
proportion of panic disorder patients
also increases anxiety and panic
disorder patients as well as among
healthy adults at these doses
so it sounds like if you have panic
disorder should not be drinking five
cups of coffee worth of caffeine
at least according to the latest
systematic review on the subject
published in
in 2022
okay Dr Greger this is Galactus
yeah you don't seem to advocate for a
mostly fruit diet why
um and so uh the video is one of my
paleo diet videos and it talks about how
whether or not we're kind of like mostly
for divorce mostly fullivores I think
was the video
um whether mostly Are we more like the
like the leaf-eating monkeys or the
fruit eating monkeys and we are more
towards the fruit eating monkeys but
that's a different thing from saying
we're frugivores uh yes fruit it's a
important part of our ancestral diet and
so why don't I recommend for mostly
fruit dad because there's an entire
class of foods that are healthier than
fruit and they're called vegetables what
is the vegetable vegetables any other
type part of the plant that's not the
fruit so there's root vegetables stem
vegetables like celery rhubarb leafy
vegetables flour vegetables like
cauliflower
um and there's actually higher nutrient
density in those then in fruits and so
if you get a lot of fruits you wouldn't
maybe not get enough vegetables in your
diet there's really so much stomach room
only somebody hours you need in the day
and so want people to get all these
other wonderful parts of the plan
into your daily diet all right Stephanie
Stephanie is confused because sometimes
uh I read you need b12 with methodox
which one should I be taking cyanical
Bauman
I already have videos saying why Santa
clausman's better I have another video
coming out because people continue to
get this message from people that are
selling you methylcobalamin because it's
more expensive but Santa Claus is more
shelf-stable
and so more likely to actually contain
B12 and since B12 is kind of important
um you want to make sure that you
actually get it so that's why I
recommend cyanica Baldwin okay and
Maxine said as well what's the worst
thing I ate recently well in five days
it's my birthday
it's my 50th birthday in five days and
so we actually just went on a nutrition
fact staff Retreat and they're so sweet
they made me a cake which was actually a
big black bean brownie so that was super
healthy but to make the 50 they did a
little marshmallows yes I ate some
marshmallows that's the worst thing I
ate recently okay
seba can I explain why sugar is bad for
our health I'm an athlete not worried
about calories so indeed sugar uh causes
cavities
um Dental cavities
um if you say well I don't care about
cavities okay so it's empty calories and
you say wait a second I don't care about
calories well so you don't worry about
getting excess calories but you know we
only have a certain amount in the
calorie Bank every day if you're an
athlete you have more than others the
concern is that you are
you know if you eat 100 calories of
sugar for example
you are in effect certainly over time
excluding 100 calories of something else
you could be eating though I mean 100
calories sugar gets you effectively is
Zero nutrition whereas 100 calories
broccoli 100 calories strawberries 100
calories almost anything else any other
whole plant food gave you tons of
nutrition and you're just leaving that
all on the table when you eat sugar
so uh yeah those are some reasons why we
shouldn't waste calories
on sugar
CEST TLD says any recommended food or
unrecommended food for type 1 diabetes
uh it'd be the same recommendation for
type 2 diabetics is type 1 diabetics
what we're trying to do is improve
insulin sensitivity so that's the
responsiveness of our liver and muscles
to insulin weather created by our
pancreas if we have type 2 diabetes or
whether it's um we inject it which is
type 1 diabetes and sometimes type 2
diabetes as well
um and so we want every unit of insulin
to do as much good as possible so we
don't have to so we inject less insulin
which is good in terms of cancer risk
and other and cost God so we are making
our body as responsive as possible and
the way we do that is we decrease our
saturated fat intake I would also say
trans fat but there's not much trans fat
in our food supply anymore so decrease
saturated fat intake that interferes
with insulin singling
um and our muscles and liver and so it
doesn't work as well
so you have to have more insulin
um either injected or pumped out from a
pancreas if you don't have type 1 to
bring blood sugars down the same amount
um so improving insulin sensitivity is
the way to go and it's the same dietary
changes centered predominantly around
increasing fiber intake and whole intact
plant foods and
um on decreasing saturated fat intake
okay
Leon
says protein protein restriction over
calorie restriction for human longevity
oh
minimize BCAAs different amino acids can
we be too low as to a detriment on Whole
Food plant-based say protein below 10
carbs oh my God this is Juicy um and
that's um not just protein restriction
in general but you know we're targeting
the silver containing amino acids like
methionine as well as the branching
amino acids but then you run into
um well what if protein gets too low do
we worry about Frailty do we worry about
sarcopenia or muscle loss with aging and
so what should our Target protein be and
um what about all the metabolic benefits
and Longevity benefits you see from
protein restriction but it's how much is
too much and so basically the answer is
um we should shoot for 0.8 grams for
healthcare gram body weight from plant
sources it's kind of the the bottom line
and that does the protein restriction
for you in terms of BCAAs methionine
although I think over age
ah 70 I was recommending uh going up to
uh to one grand prize crumb Grand by the
way don't don't uh quote me but there is
a bump later in age I forget that I
forget the age cut off but you're
totally right in thinking about this
Balancing Act and so but under 865
pentagrams for plant protein sources and
then we stick with plant protein sources
but we bump it up a little later in life
we would love it if you could share with
us your stories about Reinventing Your
Health through evidence-based nutrition
go to nutritionfacts.org testimonials we
may be able to share it on social media
to help Inspire others
see any graphs charts Graphics images or
studies mentioned here please go to the
nutrition facts podcast landing page
there you'll find all the detailed
information you need plus links to all
the sources we cite for each of these
topics
for a vital timely text on the pathogens
that cause pandemics you can order the
ebook audiobook or the hard copy of my
latest book how to survive a pandemic or
go to your local public library for that
matter for recipes check out my new how
not to diet cookbook it's beautifully
designed with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals and of
course all the proceeds I received from
all the sales of my books go to charity
nutritionfacts.org is a non-profit
science-based Public Service where you
can sign up for free daily updates on
the latest in nutrition research via
bite-sized videos and articles
everything on the website is free there
are no ads no corporate sponsorships no
Kickbacks it's strictly non-commercial
not selling anything I just put it up as
a public service as a labor of love as a
tribute to my grandmother whose own life
was saved with evidence-based nutrition